<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of passive obedience asserted in a sermon preach'd on January 30, 1684 / by James Ellesby ...</title>
            <author>Ellesby, James, b. 1644 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11960</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12835606</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12835606</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 867:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of passive obedience asserted in a sermon preach'd on January 30, 1684 / by James Ellesby ...</title>
                  <author>Ellesby, James, b. 1644 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[4] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXX, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94358:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94358:1"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF <hi>Paſſive Obedience:</hi> Aſſerted in a SERMON Preach'd on <hi>January</hi> 30. 1684.</p>
            <p>By <hi>James Ellesby, M. A.</hi> Vicar of <hi>Chiſwick</hi> in <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For Rulers are not a Terrour to good Works, but to the Evil: Wilt thou then not be afraid of the Powers? Do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 13.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple Bar.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94358:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94358:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Diſcourſe was ſent to the Preſs the <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> after it was preach'd,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 2.</note> and part of it print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the much lamented Death of his late Majesty, of moſt <hi>Dear and Happy Memory;</hi> the Intent where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was not to flatter Princes into an Abuſe of their Power, or make them more Abſolute than the Law hath done (a Calumny, which ſome are apt to faſten on the Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience;) but to teach Subjects their Duty to Governours upon all Occaſions, and inſtruct them in the Principles of Subjection, according to the Laws of the Land, and Rules of the Goſpel; wherein I have had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe Perſons, who make ſhew of a more than ordinary Zeal for Religion, yet are apparently defective in the two great Duties of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> to make them thoſe Compleat Chriſtians they would be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for.</p>
            <p>This Sermon, with another of the like nature, was at firſt preach'd ſome Years ago; now what paſs'd for good Doctrine againſt one ſort of men then, I hope will not be thought otherwiſe now; for Truth doth never alter nor
<pb facs="tcp:94358:3"/>vary with the Times, whatever the Profeſſours of it may do. I hope in God, ſeeing our Preſent Sovereign hath been pleaſed to declare (to the infinite ſatisfaction of the whole Kingdom) his Royal Intention to Govern and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue things as they are now Settled and by Law Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd, we ſhall have no reaſon to cheriſh any Fears and Jealouſies, but rather to bleſs God for inclining his Royal Heart ſo <hi>Graciouſly</hi> toward this poor Church and State. Therefore, inſtead of carrying on their old Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and Factions againſt the Government, People ought to Own and Submit to the good Providence of God, who hath preſerv'd his Majeſty that now is from ſo many imminent Dangers, and brought him to the Throne in Peace and Safety, notwithſtanding all the Attempts and Oppoſitions that have been made to the contrary. Let us then perform the Duty of good Subjects, in yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Obedience and Subjection which we owe to our <hi>Lawful Prince,</hi> and of good Chriſtians, in praying for a Bleſsing upon his Royal Perſon and Government, that he may Reign long and happily over us, and we may lead Quiet and Peaceable Lives in all Godlineſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty under him.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb. 9. 1684.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94358:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS 30.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—And a King, againſt whom there is no Riſing up.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Proverbial Sayings of the Wiſe man, carry their own Senſe and Context along with them, and are collected together without any great Order or Dependance upon one another.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of this <hi>Chapter</hi> we have <hi>Agur</hi>'s humble and modeſt Wiſh for a <hi>contented mediocrity,</hi> preferrable to both <hi>Extreams</hi> of <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Riches:</hi> The remaining part is ſpent in the obſervation of ſome remarkable Qualities, peculiar to ſeveral ſorts of Creatures.</p>
            <p>The laſt here mentioned takes notice of four things, which are Comly and Majeſtick in their Going, <hi>a Lyon which is ſtrongeſt among Beaſts, and turns not away for any; a Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound, a He-Goat, and a King, againſt whom there is no ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſpend time in giving you an account of the various Readings and Opinions of Interpreters upon theſe Words; but preferring our own Verſion as the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received, I ſhall only obſerve that the firſt and laſt of theſe, the Lyon and the King, have their particular Characters annext to them; a Lyon which is King among Beaſts, is ſo ſtrong, as he neither Fears nor Turns away from any thing; and a King, he is ſo Sacred among Men, as no Man ought to Riſe up, or Turn againſt him: The former is generally fear'd for his great Strength and undaunted Courage; and the latter, no leſs to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94358:4"/>be Reverenc'd for his Sacred Character and Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</p>
            <p>By a King here we are to underſtand a <hi>Sovereign Prince,</hi> one inveſted with the Supream Power of a Nation, and not ſuch Titular and Precarious Princes, as were the Kings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> or thoſe under thoſe <hi>Romans; Qui non proprio, ſed precario jure imperabant,</hi> in the Words of <hi>Grotius;</hi> who had little of Royalty belonging to them, beſide the Name and Ceremony, at moſt, were but Kings upon Courteſie, and reign'd at the Pleaſure of the Senate and People. But by King here is meant, ſuch a one as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> himſelf was, the ſuppoſed Author of theſe Words, under the name of <hi>Agur;</hi> one who is acknowledg'd Sovereign in his Kingdom, who holds his Crown Independant on any but God, as having no Equal, much leſs Superiour upon Earth: And ſuch a one as this the Laws do acknowledge our King to be, when they call his Crown an <hi>Imperial Crown,</hi> reſembling that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, which was <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Independant;</hi> when they Entitle him upon all Occaſions, <hi>Our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> when they account his Perſon <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Inviolable,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but in reſpect of his Authority, which muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be Divine in its Original, and Inſeparable from his Perſon; when they affirm he is <hi>Legibus Solutus,</hi> free from the Coercive Power of the Law; and enjoyn us to pray for him as <hi>Supream in all Cauſes, and over all Perſons, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Majeſties Realms and Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt ſuch a King as this, there is no Riſing up, that is, there ought to be none: No Force or Violence, no Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or Reſiſtance can lawfully be made againſt a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Prince, who receives his Power immediately from God, and therefore to him alone can be accountable for it.</p>
            <p>From the Words thus open'd, you may eaſily gheſs at the Subject Matter, and Intent of my enſuing Diſcourſe, which will be to prove, and if poſſibly, convince you of the great Sin and Danger of Reſiſting a <hi>Supream Lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94358:4"/>wherever it is lodg'd, either in one or more, and upon what Account it becomes utterly unlawful ſo to do.</p>
            <p>§. Now that <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> of this nature is a Sin, I am throughly ſatisfied, and the Reaſons why I believe ſo, are ſuch as follow.</p>
            <p>§. 1. Becauſe it is an Affront and Violation offered to a Divine Ordinance, and that Government is a Divine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance I might prove at large, from the Teſtimony of all Nations concerning it; from the joynt Confeſſion of the whole Chriſtian Church, Primitive and Reform'd, and in particular by that of our own, together with the Laws of the Land, which do acknowledge and ſuppoſe as much. But however, there is leſs need of inſiſting upon theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth expreſly affirm it, and this he doth by a Spirit of greater Infallibility than that of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other Sect or Party of Men, who have taught the contrary. Rom. 13.1, 2. <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that be are ordain'd of God, whoſoever therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſisteth the powers, reſisteth the Ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that Reſiſtance is an Affront thereunto, I think none will deny, for it is to overthrow what God himſelf hath Eſtabliſh'd, to pluck up what he hath Planted, and to make void, as much as in us lies, the Providence of God in the Government of the World.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Gamaliel</hi>'s Argument to the Councel, that they ſhould not evil intreat the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>lest haply they ſhould be found to fight againſt God.</hi> The like caution may be given in this Caſe, that no Man ought to offer the leaſt reſiſtance to Civil Authority, nor ſo much as lift up a hand or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt thoſe whom God hath ſet over them, leſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they be ſound at length to ſight againſt God, in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Vicegerent. For our Saviour's way of Reaſoning, which he uſeth in another Inſtance, for vindicating the Miſſion and Authority of his Apoſtles, holds good here; <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> In like manner, he that offers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94358:5"/>reſiſtance to the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>Sovereign,</hi> doth in that very Act, reſiſt the Ordinance of God, and he that reſiſteth a Divine Ordinance, may be ſaid to reſiſt God himſelf, who is the Sole Author and Inſtitutor thereof; and what a Man may expect after ſuch an Affront, I need not tell him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</note> for the Apoſtle doth, <hi>They that Reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 2. Reſiſtance is the breach of a Divine Command, and in that reſpect the Abettors thereof can't be Guiltleſs: Is not Obedience and Subjection to Civil Authority made our Duty, and preſt upon us frequently in Holy Writ, as well in the Old Teſtament as the New; The particular Places to this purpoſe are ſo well known that I need not repeat them at large; that of the Text is ſufficient at preſent.</p>
            <p>Now it is granted on all hands, that a Divine Command reacheth the Conſcience: God therefore having given us an expreſs command for Subjection, hath thereby made it our Duty, and having given us an expreſs Prohibition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reſiſtance hath made that a Sin, and conſequently matter of Conſcience to every Chriſtian: For Conſcience muſt evermore have a Divine Command for its Direction and Guide, for its Rule and Warrant to Act by, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 'tis not Conſcience, but ſomething elſe that deſerves a worſe Name. Now conſider, a thing becomes never the more Lawful or Unlawful in it ſelf, becauſe it is grown a Cuſtom and Faſhion with ſome Men to plead Conſcience for or againſt it; except you will grant that Conſcience is Infallible in all Men alike, or that a Man can't do amiſs, or go wrong, that pretends to follow the Dictates of his Conſcience; for then, when two Perſons Act directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to one another, both may be ſaid to be in the right, if they do but follow, their Conſciences, the one in doing, the other in Forbearing what they are commanded.</p>
            <p>Conſcience then being ſo variable, is no Rule at all, much leſs an infallible Rule, but ſtands in need of one that is ſo; for want of which, it hath been greatly miſtaken;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94358:5"/>therefore that only becomes neceſſary to be done, which God hath commanded, and that only Sinful and Unlawful which he hath forbidden.</p>
            <p>Now let us bring this home to the Caſe in hand. By this Rule, all Seditious Practices, and violent Attempts againſt the Government, being forbidden by God, are as much Sins as any Act of Prophaneſs and Impiety whatſoever; and are never the more Warrantable, becauſe ſome Men have pleaded Conſcience in Defence thereof, and diſguis'd their Faction under the Veil of Religion. Well therefore may we apply that of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19.5.24.</note> which hath been ſo oft urg'd againſt this very Duty; <hi>Whether is better to be Obey'd, God or Man, judge ye.</hi> So in this matter, Whether ought to be moſt obeyed? God, who commands Subjection, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids Reſiſtance; or ſuch Turbulent, and Diſaffected Perſons, who plead Conſcience againſt every thing they diſlike, and pretend Religion to the neglect of this Duty, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a poſitive Precept and Divine Command?</p>
            <p>The Text tells us, againſt a King there is no Riſing up: that is, as I have already told you, there ought to be none. Had the People but the tenth part as much for Reſiſtance, as here is againſt it, no Government would be quiet, nor Kings ſuffer'd to ſit long upon their Thrones; when yet they are in ſo much danger, from the Patrons of Faction and Sedition, notwithſtanding all the Proviſion which God himſelf hath made for their Security.</p>
            <p>This will further appear, if we conſider the Inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it to our Chriſtian Profeſſion. Wherefore,</p>
            <p>§ 3. Reſiſtance, or Oppoſition to Civil Government, is contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt; Examples of the Apoſtles, and the whole Genius and Deſign of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of Chriſt is well known, and hath been ſufficiently vindicated upon this Occaſion. It recommends to its Profeſſors all thoſe admirable Vertues and Graces,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94358:6"/>which are inconſiſtent with a fierce and violent temper of Mind: It Enjoyns us to pray for our Enemies, and bleſs our Perſecutors: tho we ſuffer wrongfully, to bear it patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; to do Good for Evil, inſtead of returning it: to take up the Croſs rather than the Sword; for which <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo ſharply rebuk'd by his Maſter and Ours. Now there can be no Reſiſtance but ſomething of Revenge muſt prompt to it, and be mingled with it.</p>
            <p>Now if by the Laws of our Religion we are forbid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or the returning of Wrong towards our Equals and Inferiours, much more towards our Superiours. For if Love and Charity is due to the one, Faith and Loyalty being ſuperadded thereto, is due to the Other. And if to ſuffer, tho wrongfully, be a Duty; be ſure wrongful Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is no leſs a Crime. Now all Reſiſtance is of this kind, for want of a Lawful Authority to bear it out.</p>
            <p>§. Then for the Example of Chriſt; this was nothing elſe but a <hi>Praxis</hi> upon his own Doctrine; inſtructing them therein, as well by his meek and gentle Behaviour, as by his admirable Counſel and Advice. Though his Cauſe was the moſt Juſt and Righteous, and himſelf the moſt innocent Perſon in the World; tho his Enemies were the moſt Cruel, and his Sufferings the moſt Severe, attended with all the Circumſtances of Ignominy and Reproach; yet the great Saviour of the World, and Exemplar of us Chriſtians, was ſo far from offering at Reſiſtance, or any thing like it, that he did not utter ſo much as a threatning Word, nor make ſhew of the leaſt Murmuring or Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.7.</note> 
               <hi>But as a ſheep before the Shearers is dumb, ſo he opened not his Mouth;</hi> ſaith the Evangelical Prophet. <hi>Who when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he ſuffered, he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter</hi> 2.23.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Now the more we reſemble our meek and humble Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in our Comportment under Sufferings and Injuries,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94358:6"/>the greater aſſurance we have of being his Diſciples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; this will entitle us to the Adoption of Sons, and make us Heirs with him of the promiſed Reward.</p>
            <p>§. Add to the Example of Chriſt, that of his Apoſtles, who were in all reſpects admirable Followers of the Bleſſed Jeſus; inſtead of revenging their Sufferings, or reſiſting the Powers under which they ſuffered, they on the quite contrary rejoye'd in Affliction, and gloried in Tribulation; they accounted it an Honour to tread in the ſteps of their great Maſter, and to be ſo evil intreated by the World for His ſake.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis not only the Cauſe, but the Manner of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or our Behaviour under it, that makes our Sufferings like thoſe of Chriſts; for let our Sufferings be upon what account they will, whether Civil or Religious, 'tis our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and Submiſſive Demeanour under them, that makes them Chriſtian Sufferings, and to reſemble thoſe of our Bleſſed Redeemer; nay, the Manner of Suffering is every whit as much to be regarded as the Occaſion; for a Man may ſuffer in a good Cauſe after a bad manner, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by loſe the Reward of his Sufferings for want of Faith and Patience to ſupport and carry him through: Again, He that ſuffers in an ill Cauſe, may become ſo Senſible of his Fault, and Penitent withall, as to find Pity from Man and Pardon from God; whereas the beſt Cauſe can never juſtify the impatient murmurings and diſcontent of its fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Martyrs or peeviſh Confeſſors.</p>
            <p>§. To this purpoſe, let us conſider a while the Example of the Primitive Chriſtians, how they behav'd themſelves under all their Perſecutions, and we ſhall find them Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Apoſtles, as they were of Chriſt, and thereby prov'd themſelves no leſs his Scholars and Diſciples than they. We find them made up of Patience and Submiſſion, Meekneſs and Long-ſuffering; they underwent the greateſt Rage, ſharpeſt Torments, and ſevereſt Perſecutions that could be, yet with an Apoſtolical temper, and Chriſt-like
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94358:7"/>frame and diſpoſition of Mind, amid'ſt all the Cruelties threatned on the one hand, and inflicted on the other, we find nothing could provoke them to a Diſturbance; we read of nothing they did in way of Revenge or Deſpite to their Governours; and notwithſtanding the late diſingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Repreſentation of the Chriſtians in <hi>Julian</hi>'s Time, yet from the beſt Account we have given us of that, and the Preceding Ages, we are aſſur'd, that the Patience of the Chriſtians was equal to the Rage of their Adverſaries, and their Conſtancy and Reſolution in bearing Injuries, was greater than that of their Enemies in the inflicting of them.</p>
            <p>Nay, their Sufferings were rather cauſe of Joy and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, than of Quarrel and Revenge: <hi>Magis damnati quam abſoluti gaudemus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. ad Scapul.</note> ſaid the moſt Ancient of all the <hi>Latine</hi> Fathers: We are more chearful at the news of our Condemnation than of our Acquittal or Abſolution: Now their willingneſs to ſuffer, and forwardneſs to ſubmit, is an Argument they were much better Chriſtians than the generality of thoſe, who think themſelves in the uppermoſt Form in Chriſt's School, and yet have not taken out this Leſſon.</p>
            <p>What kind of Weapons thoſe were which the Primitive Chriſtians oppoſed to all the Abuſes and Outrages of their Adverſaries, is very well known: They made uſe of no Offenſive Arms againſt the very worſt of Princes, nor any other Defence than that of Prayers and Tears, Apologies and Supplications; <hi>aliter nec debeo nec poſſum reſiſtere,</hi> ſays the Warlike Biſhop of <hi>Milan.</hi> According to the Principles of their Religion, they could not make any other Defence, they were not permitted any other Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>And therefore one great Topick they inſiſted on in their Apologies for themſelves and their Religion was this, That it was the greateſt friend to Government in the World; it no ways countenanc'd Sedition, nor encourag'd to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; but on the contrary, kept Subjects within the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94358:7"/>ſtricteſt bounds of Obedience, made them Loyal to the Prince, and Faithful to the Government, and bound it as a Duty upon their Conſciences ſo to be: It taught them to reſpect their Governours as God's Miniſters and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents upon Earth; to acknowledge with our Saviour, that they receiv'd their Power from above, and to behave themſelves under it accordingly.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, that you may ſee how ſhy they were of Reſiſtance, and at what a diſtance they kept from this Sin, they were wont to put up Publick Prayers (and I dare ſay they never ſaid them <hi>backward</hi> in Private) for the Life of the Emperour, Safety of his Perſon, and Succeſs of his Arms, tho in ſo doing they did but pray for their greateſt Enemies, Perſecutors and Slanderers, and a continuance of all thoſe Calamities which they daily ſuffered and groan'd under.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> This in a great meaſure Some will acknowledge to be true, but not upon the Principles of Conſcience and Religion: 'tis true, ſay they, the Primitive Chriſtians did not reſiſt, but it was becauſe they durſt not; <hi>Deerant vires,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> they wanted Strength and Numbers to oppoſe and go through with it, if they had begun, and therefore it was <hi>Prudence</hi> in them to ſit ſtill and be quiet, and make the beſt they could of an ill Bargain, as having no hopes to better it by Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This Objection or Pretence carries a great deal of Untruth along with it, and no leſs Ill Will and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection toward Governours; but in reality is no better than a Jeſuitical Fiction, made uſe of by that Order of men (who make Lyes their refuge, when they find the plain Truth is not for their turn) to ſupport their wicked Doctrine of taking up Arms againſt the Prince at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their Church. For if any credit may be given to Primitive Antiquity and the General Hiſtory of thoſe Times, the Chriſtians then had both Arms and Armies; They wanted not Force to Defend themſelves, and Oppoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94358:8"/>their Governours, if they had had a mind to it; For the chiefeſt part of the Empire was then turn'd Chriſtian, who made up <hi>partom poene majorem,</hi> the greateſt Number almoſt in every Town and City, ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> whoſe account is very well known, and daily cited upon this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if they had been inclin'd to Reſiſtance, or thought it Lawful, might not the <hi>Deſperatoneſs</hi> of their Caſe have ſupply'd the defect of their Numbers, which ſometimes carries men a great way, and inſpires them with Courage and Reſolution beyond that of their Enemies; conſidering withall, their Condition could not well be worſe than it was, had they failed in their Attempt, and fallen ſhort of Succeſs; for let what would happen, they could but Dy, and it was more Honourable (for Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers eſpecially) to dye in the Field, than at a Stake or Gibbet, and more ſatisfaction to ſell their Lives as dear as they could, than to have them torn away from them by all imaginable Torture and inſulting Cruelty.</p>
            <p>But, God be praiſed, none of theſe Conſiderations mov'd them: They were acted by other-gueſs Maximes and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, than the diſaffected of this preſent Age: We hear of no Attempts, or Offers of Reſiſtance, amidſt the greateſt heats of Perſecution; and it is a mighty Credit to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and Satisfaction to all good Chriſtians, that no ſuch thing is recorded of them: This argues the Goodneſs both of their Cauſe and Religion, which upon that Account, deſervedly recommends it ſelf to the eſpecial Care and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Princes; as being the beſt Fence and Security to their Perſons and Government.</p>
            <p>§. 4. Reſiſtance againſt Lawful Authority is a Sin that doth moſt commonly meet with its Shame and Puniſhment even in this Life, and hath evermore been Abhor'd by all Good Men, notwithſtanding the Succeſs, which for a time it may meet withall.</p>
            <p>No Crime is judg'd more Wicked and Unnatural, more Miſchievous and Prejudicial to Humane Society than this;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94358:8"/>and no greater Puniſhment aſſign'd to any, than to this of Treaſon and Rebellion, which is the plain Engliſh of all Violent Reſiſtance, when oppos'd to Lawful Authority; it being of moſt dangerous Conſequence to all States, and no Government long Safe, where this may be permitted, or thought Lawful; and therefore the Laws of all Nations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven have ſtrictly provided againſt this Sin, and branded it with the greateſt Reproach and Infamy in the World. It forfeits not only the Life and Eſtate of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty guilty thereof, but Taints his Blood, Ignobles his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and is too oft the Ruine and Diſhonour of many otherwiſe Splendid and Illuſtrious Families; eſpecially where the Prince is pleas'd to take the Forfeiture, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the utmoſt Rigour and Extremity of the Law. <hi>Eſt enim tam grave Crimen, ut vix permittatur Haeredibus, quod vivant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bracton;</hi> 'tis ſo Vile and Infamous a piece of Guilt, that the Law doth hardly allow Life to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Poſterity.</p>
            <p>Had I time, I might obſerve unto you, out of all ſorts of Hiſtory, and the Records of all Nations extant, the Sore and Grievous Puniſhments, which have overtaken thoſe that have been given to Change, and drawn into Open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, or ſecret Conſpiracy againſt their Lawful Prince and Governours; which is a manifeſt token, how much God and Man abhors this Sin, and how dangerous it is to thoſe that are Guilty thereof.</p>
            <p>The Time would fail me to ſpeak of the juſt Judgment of God, purſuing <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> who roſe up againſt <hi>Moſes; Abſalom, Achitophel,</hi> and <hi>Sheba,</hi> who rebelled againſt <hi>David:</hi> befalling <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh,</hi> which conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt <hi>Ahaſuerus; Theudas</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> who made an Inſurrection under the <hi>Romans:</hi> overtaking the Murderers of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> his Son, and the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators againſt the ſeveral Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> All which are recorded in Holy Writ to be like <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, when turn'd into a Pillar of Salt, as ſo many ſtanding Monuments,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94358:9"/>to caution us againſt this horrid Guilt: where unto I might add out of prophane Story, the Murderers of <hi>Darius, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, J. Caeſar,</hi> and an infinite more who have been all brought to a Shameful and Untimely End by this very Sin, and Branded to Poſterity for their deteſtable Treaſons and Conſpiracies againſt their Princes and Sovereigns.</p>
            <p>§. The whole Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were very Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Quiet under both their former Captivities and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Account always far'd the better for it, God himſelf inclining the Hearts of their Conquerours toward them, and ſometimes appearing in an Extraordinary manner for their Safety and Deliverance, yet were at laſt utterly Ruin'd by this very Sin; for by Rebelling againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> they became a dreadful Inſtance of God's Wrath and Severity; firſt under <hi>Titus,</hi> and afterward under <hi>Adrian,</hi> by whom, for their frequent Mutinies and Inſurrections, they were baniſh'd their Countrey, forbid their City, and every foot of Land taken from them, which they could never recover from that time to this.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I or can I ſay more; the great Conſcience which <hi>David</hi> made of Reſiſting <hi>Saul,</hi> Injuring his Perſon, or Attempting ought againſt his Government, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was Choſen of God and Anointed by <hi>Samuel</hi> to the Succeſſion; as likewiſe his puniſhing the wicked <hi>Amalekite</hi> with Death for laying hands upon him, tho in his Diſtreſs, and at his Requeſt, to prevent his Fall into the Enemies hands; All theſe Inſtances give us to underſtand (if we will Underſtand any thing) how Hateful and Abominable this Sin is both to God and Man; and how much we ſhould dread all Beginnings and Approches thereunto.</p>
            <p>§. I pray, what have the Authours of the late Rebellion, and in particular of this Days horrible Parricide, what have they got thereby, but beſides the Forfeiture of their Lives and Eſtates, a Stain upon their Memories, a Reproach to their Religion, and Cauſe of perpetual Jealouſie and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion from the Government?</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94358:9"/>
            <p>The like may be affirm'd of all thoſe who have been any ways Inſtrumental in carrying on the two late Horrid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt the Life of our Preſent King, (whom I pray God long preſerve) what have they got hereby, but as the Prophet ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.40.</note> 
               <hi>an Everlasting Reproach and a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Blot, which ſhall not be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He therefore that takes the Sword into his hand to lift it up againſt his Brother, much more againſt the Father of his Countrey, doth in that very Act reſcue it out of Gods hand, and ſo may juſtly dread the Fatal Conſequence of ſuch a Preſumption, foretold by our Saviour, when he ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.52.</note> 
               <hi>They that take the Sword ſhall Periſh with it;</hi> which moſt Men have found true to their own Coſt, either firſt or laſt, ſooner or later: Wherefore you ought to be Subject (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>for Wrath ſake,</hi> that is, for fear of the juſt Judgement of God overtaking you in this Life, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from his own hand, or that of the Magiſtrate: But this is not all, there is ſomething <hi>Worſe</hi> than this yet behind; wherefore,</p>
            <p>§. 5. God hath threatned to puniſh this Sin with <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> Rom. 13.2. ſo the Text runs according to our Verſion: The word indeed ſignifies <hi>Judgment;</hi> but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, according to the Analogy of Scripture, it may refer to the Puniſhment of the Other Life as well as of This, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Reſiſtance is (as you have heard) the breach of a Divine Command, the <hi>Tranſgreſſion of the Law of God,</hi> which the Apoſtle tells us is Sin;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>now the Wages of Sin is Death,</hi> that is, of all Sin, and This among the reſt: and then what a woful Caſe muſt they be in, who Live and Dye in this Sin unrepented of, or whom the juſt Judgement of God doth overtake before they are brought to an Humble Senſe and Acknowledgement thereof.</p>
            <p>Now who would venture upon this Sin, which carries Shame in the Front, and Damnation in the Rear? Who would hazard his Soul, tho it were for the Conqueſt of the whole World, much leſs for a ſmall clod and parcel thereof.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94358:10"/>
            <p>Strangel that Chriſtians, who know they have Souls to ſave, or loſe for ever; and therefore ſhould be the moſt ſcrupulous of any thing that might hazard and endanger them, that yet they ſhould be able to allow themſelves in ſo great a Guilt; and ſtudy all they can for Pretences to excuſe and mitigate this Sin, rather than take Warning and Repent thereof; notwithſtanding ſo vaſt a Puniſhment is threatned thereto.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Particular, Whatever we may dream of the Original of the Magiſtrates Power, yet our Religion for certain teaches us to acknowledge it to be Divine, and to proceed from God: It makes Subjection, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Evaſions and Pretences to the contrary, to become our Duty, and that as well for Conſcience, as Wrath ſake; and doth moreover caution us againſt Reſiſtance, as a great and Damning Sin, Deſtructive to the Souls, as well as Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Men; and being ſo, what is there in this World that is worth the hazarding our Souls for; what kind of Chriſtians muſt they be, that can ſwallow down a Sin of this Nature ſo glib, and digeſt it ſo lightly; and what kind of Subjects are they that ſhall go about to wreſt the Laws, as ſome have done the Scriptures, in Favour of this Sin; a Sin ſo abominable in the ſight of God,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23.</note> that as <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul, Rebellion was as the Sin of Witchcraft:</hi> and that is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſaith a Modern Writer, that the Devil was ſo forward to tempt the <hi>Jews</hi> to it of old, and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of late; <hi>Wherefore my Soul come not thou into their Secrets, and unto their Aſſemblies be not thou united.</hi> Gen. 49.6.</p>
            <p>§. I come now to conſider the chiefeſt Objections that are uſually made uſe of againſt this Doctrine, which I ſhall endeavour to Anſwer in the Reſolution of theſe three great Inquiries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether Subjection is due to Bad Governours as well as Good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether it continues our Duty, when Religion is in apparent Hazard and Danger. And,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94358:10"/>3. When the Laws of the Land, or which is all one, when the Civil Rights and Liberties of the Subject are invaded.</p>
            <p>To all which I anſwer, Yes; Submiſſion is our Duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all theſe Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>§. 1. As to the firſt Inquiry; Let our Governours be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo Bad, Actual Obedience is due to all their Lawful Commands, and Submiſſion to thoſe that are Otherwiſe; but in no caſe Reſiſtance to either. For what the Apoſtle adviſeth Servants toward their Maſters, holds equally true on the behalf of Subjects towards their Governours, where the Obligation is much ſtronger, namely,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>To be ſubject with all Fear, not only to the Good and Gentle, but alſo to the Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:</hi> which <hi>Grotius,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> before him, refers to Princes and Subjects, as well as to Maſters and Servants: For as the Authority of the Maſter, ſo the Power of the Prince, of the Evil and Froward, as well as of the Good and Gentle, is from God; tho the Perſon may be Wicked and Ungodly, yet his Authority is Sacred and Divine, and in that reſpect commands our Reverence, as being the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God. For <hi>Dominion</hi> is not founded in <hi>Grace,</hi> neither do the <hi>Temporal Rights</hi> of Princes depend upon Religion, whether <hi>True</hi> or <hi>Falſe;</hi> the Power of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is never the more from God, becauſe he is a Good man, and never the leſs from God, becauſe he is a Bad man; but the Authority of the Good and Bad is alike in Both, and derived from one and the ſame Original, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Abuſe thereof when in Ill hands: To this purpoſe that of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is very well known;
<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>l. de natura Boni adv.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich. <hi>c.</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>Etiam Nocenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Poteſtas non eſt niſi à Deo; The Power even of Hurtful Princes or Tyrants is from God:</hi> and in the fifth Book of his City of God, He inſtanceth in the Beſt and Worſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, <hi>Qui Auguſto, Ipſe &amp; Neroni, &amp;c. Qui Conſtantino Chriſtiano, Ipſe Apostatae Juliano, &amp;c.</hi> He that gave the Sovereign Power to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> gave it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to <hi>Nero;</hi> and He that confer'd it upon <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> a Chriſtian, beſtow'd it in like manner upon <hi>Julian</hi> an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94358:11"/>and this, ſaith he, <hi>Si occultis cauſis nunquid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtis?</hi> tho by hidden Cauſes, and for ſecret Reaſons to us unknown, yet ſuch as are never Unjuſt.</p>
            <p>The Abuſe therefore of a Lawful Power in the Prince, is no excuſe for an unlawful Act in the Subject, as Reſiſtance is; for if the Prince receives his Power from God, to him only muſt he be Accountable for it; but the Subjects caſe is different, for if he fails in his Duty, he is Accountable both to God and his Governours. Authority then however manag'd, ought not to be oppos'd, ſeeing God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed no ſuch thing, nor given Subjects any ſuch Permiſſion; but they ought to obey as far as lawfully they may, and where they cannot do that, then to ſit ſtill and be Quiet, Submit to the good Pleaſure of God, and prepare for Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, when He in his Providence ſhall call them to it, as then he doth when they cannot avoid it without Sin.</p>
            <p>For pray conſider, If we muſt preſently fly to Arms, or break forth into open Force and Reſiſtance upon the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of Government, or becauſe perchance we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious thereto, and may think our ſelves in ſome Danger to ſuffer under it; pray, what then will become of the <hi>Faith and Patience of the Saints,</hi> ſo much celebrated in Scripture, and ſpoken of in Former Times? Where would be that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Forbearance, Long-ſuffering, and Self denial, which our Religion enjoyns in Times of Suffering and Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Bad Princes and Governours.</p>
            <p>The great Evangelical Duties of Meekneſs, Patience, and Submiſſion to the Will of God, which are preſt ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon Chriſtians by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Are they of Force only under Good Princes, and not under Bad? Under Good Princes there is commonly little or no need of them; and if they are not of Force under Bad, there is never like to be any Occaſion for them at all; and then the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons given us in Scripture concerning them, become alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Vain, and to no purpoſe in the World; which muſt needs reflect upon the Divine Wiſdom, in enjoyning us Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94358:11"/>of ſuch a Nature, as have no time Time or Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the Practice of them: but none, I hope, will dare to charge God thus fooliſhly.</p>
            <p>In a Word, Chriſtians, if you are reſolved to obey and ſubmit only to the Good and Gentle, and not to the Evil and Froward; if you are reſolved to be Peaceable and Complying, ſo long as things are like to go well on your ſide, and no longer; I may well demand of you in the Words of our Saviour to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> What do you more than others? Do not the very Heathens and Publicans the ſame? Are not the worſt of Men as good Subjects as this comes to? And do you think the Religion of Chriſt doth teach you to be no better than they: Your Righteouſneſs even in this Reſpect muſt exceed that of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> if ever you hope to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>§. 2. In Anſwer to the ſecond Objection, 'tis not the Cauſe of God, nor Preſervation of Religion, that can juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Reſiſtance of a Lawful Authority; for Religion it ſelf, as you have heard, doth forbid it. Now for Men to aſſert Religion by Actions Unlawful, and ſuch as Religion it ſelf doth condemn, is very Abſurd and Prepoſterous. This is in effect to make void Religion, while they ſtand up in the Defence thereof, and to tranſgreſs the Laws of Chriſtianity, at the ſame time that they contend ſo fiercely for them.</p>
            <p>To defend Religion by Rebellious Force, is to violate Religion for <hi>Religions Sake;</hi> and to defeat the great End and Deſign of the Goſpel, out of a Zeal to the Name, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Thing,</p>
            <p>Give me leave therefore to be a little warm with thoſe People, who uſe to be much <hi>hotter</hi> upon this Occaſion; You that think your ſelves oblig'd to ſcuffle with your Prince, out of Zeal to your Religion, Pray, What Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is it, that you would contend for? Is it for a Religion that Encourageth Sedition, Countenanceth Rebellion, teaches Reſiſtance, and Puts you upon Violent Courſes on its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94358:12"/>If this be the Religion you would Tugg for, 'tis fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that both you and your Religion too ſhould be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt and kept under: For <hi>ſuch Religion</hi> as this, is nothing but Rebellion in Diſguiſe; and <hi>ſuch Faith,</hi> nothing but Faction under a Vail. This is ſuch a Religion that no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the World will endure, go where you will; no nor your ſelves neither, if you were uppermoſt; and doth it become Chriſtians to plead Conſcience for ſuch a Religion as would put them upon the moſt Infamous and Diſhonourable Practices, and render them Odious and Suſpected to all Governments under Heaven.</p>
            <p>But on the other Hand, Is it the Religion of Chriſt, the Doctrine of the Goſpel, and Pure Chriſtianity, that you would ſtruggle for? Why this very Goſpel and Religion teaches you quite otherwiſe; 'tis an Humble, Quiet, and Peaceable Religion; of the greateſt Meekneſs, Forbearance, and Self-denial; a Religion that is made up of nothing but Love and Charity, Peace and Unity, Forgiveneſs and Long-ſuffering; a Religion that abhors Violence, damns Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and ſtrictly prohibits the uſe of Force and Violence on its behalf, as contrary to its own Genius, together with that of its Author: Now to pretend any of theſe for the Sake of ſuch a Religion as this, is the greateſt Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on imaginable.</p>
            <p>We muſt not do Evil, that Good may come of it, is a known <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> in Chriſtianity: We muſt not willingly do an Ill thing tho it be for God himſelf; The <hi>Ark</hi> (for inſtance) muſt fall, or we muſt venture it at leaſt, rather then ſupport it by a Wrong Hand, or too Rude an Arm: We ought not with <hi>Peter</hi> to draw the Sword againſt a Lawful Authority, tho it be in defence of the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the World; but quietly permit him to be taken and ſlain, tho wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and by wicked Hands; rather then attempt his Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue in an Unwarrantable manner. Agreeable hereunto, we ought not to undertake either the Safety, or Reformation of Religion in ſuch a way as God himſelf doth diſapprove
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94358:12"/>of: Such men, inſtead of hoping to be Accepted for their Zeal, may be ſent away with a <hi>Quis requiſivit?</hi> or <hi>who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> Wherefore thoſe Pretences of Religion are never to be Truſted, which tend to any Ill Deſign againſt the Government, or are Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with any part of our Chriſtian Duty, whereof this of Subjection is none of the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither will the Invaſion of the <hi>Laws,</hi> or which is all one, of our <hi>Civil Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> juſtifie Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the Sovereign.</p>
            <p>But now, becauſe People are apt to be Alarum'd, and Object in this caſe: That if we muſt not ſtand up in the Defence of our Laws and Liberties, when they chance to be invaded, this is the ready way to invite Injuries and Oppreſſions from the Prince, to enſlave a <hi>Freeborn</hi> People, and open the Door for <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Sway and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to come in upon us, without any hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs in ſuch a Grievous Caſe: To this I ſhall reply in the following particulars.</p>
            <p>§ 1. We may endeavour the Security and Preſervation of our Liberties and Eſtates by all Lawful means, in a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal way, and after a Modeſt, Humble, and Peaceable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, ſuch as the Laws of the Land do allow of, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with that Duty and Reſpect, which by the Law of God we owe our Prince.</p>
            <p>§ 2. Let our Circumſtances be never ſo hard and Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, yet to go about to Remedy them by Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and Oppoſition, is the worſt way we can poſſibly take. For this is a Courſe which is both <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis firſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> and that according to the Laws both of God and Man.</p>
            <p>§ 1. 'Tis Unallowable by the Laws of God, or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Principles of Religion, as I have already prov'd at large from the Doctrine and Example of Chriſt, and the Practice of the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtianity. For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94358:13"/>hereby, we are taught to Suffer as the <hi>Servants</hi> of Chriſt, rather than reſiſt as <hi>Free-men</hi> of the Nation: And tho want of Prudence and Policy may be objected in the caſe, yet they are never to be pleaded to the prejudice of our Conſciences in the Breach of any known Religious Duty.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, to ſit ſtill and Suffer rather than Riſe up and Reſiſt, is <hi>Durus Sermo,</hi> a hard Leſſon; but yet is ſuch a Leſſon that God hath ſet us, and muſt be learnt, as making up a conſiderable part of our Religion: It may be thought <hi>Fooliſh</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable</hi> at firſt ſight, and in the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of moſt men, but will appear quite otherwiſe upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Thoughts, when conſidered according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>However, let it appear as Imprudent and Impolitick as it will to men of corrupt Minds, yet the <hi>Policy</hi> of this World ought to give way to the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the Goſpel; and if God hath once made it our Duty, 'tis not all the Objections drawn from Intereſt and Reaſons of State that can make it otherwiſe, except the Argument holds good, that we were <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> before we were <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and ſo ought to prefer the Rights and Priviledges of the One, before the great Commands and Duties of the Other.</p>
            <p>But then at this way of arguing we may Superſede the whole Law of God, and Evade the chiefeſt part of our Chriſtian Duty, when once it ſtands in the way of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Ambition. For are we not <hi>Men</hi> as well as <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and have we not <hi>Honour, Credit,</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> to be tender of, as well as <hi>Privileges?</hi> Why then may we not plead the One againſt Conſcience and Duty as well as the Other? What more Mean and Cowardly, may the <hi>Proud</hi> man ſay, than to to turn one Cheek when we are ſmitten on the other, to forbear Revenge upon an Injury offer'd, or put up an Affront with Patience, and requite it with Kindneſs; This to a man of more <hi>Honour</hi> than <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> ſounds Low and Mean, appears Baſe and Ignoble, and yet no Duty can be more Chriſtian than This. Now if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94358:13"/>it is not warrantable to oppoſe any of theſe Worldly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations to the greater Obligation of Conſcience in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of forgiving Enemies, and paſſing by Injuries; no more ought we to object againſt the Duty in Hand, upon any Politick Motive or Conſideration whatever.</p>
            <p>Doth our Religion oblige us to bear and endure ſo much from one another, and nothing at all from our Rulers; to lay aſide Malice and Revenge, Hatred and Ill Will towards our Equals and Inferiours, and not to do the like towards our Superiours, and thoſe whom God in his Providence hath advanced ſo much above us. This <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> therefore being enjoyn'd by Chriſt, becomes as much our Duty towards our Governours, as the Other of <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> is our Duty to each other.</p>
            <p>§. From the Doctrine, let me deſire you to turn your Eyes once more upon the Example of Chriſt, and mark his Behaviour a little more narrowly: As he was no <hi>Hector</hi> to return an Affront immediately, or as ſoon as it was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd; ſo neither did he ſet up for a <hi>Champion</hi> or <hi>Patriot</hi> of his Country againſt his Duty to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour; he never eſpouſed the Cauſe of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a Faction, or carry on a Party againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: He would not Aſſert the Liberties and Priviledges of his Country-men (tho they enjoy'd them by a Divine Grant) in prejudice to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Authority, or to the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting of the Publick Peace; ſo great a Friend he was to the Quiet of the World, and ſo little Encouragement did he give to the Diſturbers of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> had many good Laws to be govern'd by, and great Priviledges belonging to them; inſomuch as it was not lawful to bind a <hi>Roman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 22.25.</note> or beat him with Rods like an ordinary Malefactor, as in the Caſe of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> Yet the Primitive Chriſtians (many of whom were <hi>Romans,</hi> and born to thoſe Priviledges which others purchas'd) never laid claim to any of them to the Prejudice of their Duty towards the higher Powers; but choſe to ſuffer and part with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94358:14"/>all, even to Life it ſelf, (which alone is ſufficient to weigh down all the Reſt) rather than ſave either the one or the other by Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>If then the great Concern of Life ought not to exempt us from Subjection, then ſurely no other Conveniencies or Advantages relating thereunto can poſſibly do it: For are we not commanded to part with Lands and Livings, Friends and Relations, rather than Deny Chriſt, or any part of his Religion, as this of Subjection to Governours is, and a conſiderable part too.</p>
            <p>And how Extravagant ſoever ſuch a piece of Self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al may be look't upon in or by the World; yet this ſhould not Move a Chriſtian, who hath a Soul to be concern'd for, of more worth than the whole World, and all the Honours and Advantages thereof put together: This for certain will ſecure our Condition with reſpect to a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State, whatever may happen or fall out in This; whenas all our Loſſes and Sufferings in this World ſhall be abundantly made up with <hi>a rich Recompence of Reward,</hi> and <hi>a far more Exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory;</hi> wherefore, Chriſtians, comfort one another with theſe Hopes. But, ſecondly.</p>
            <p>§. 2. To put the matter out of all doubt, Reſiſtance is Unlawful according to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land; For the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of our <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> of our <hi>Parliaments</hi> have ſufficiently provided againſt Taking up of Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King or his Miniſters: and to This the whole Nation have Sworn, and given their Aſſent once already by their <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> and every man doth it over again in his own Perſon, as oft as they are admitted to any Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employment either in Church or State.</p>
            <p>Our Laws are accounted in all reſpects as <hi>Loyal</hi> as our Religion, and I make no queſtion, but the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of that <hi>Honourable Science</hi> are better able to vindicate them herein, than I can poſſibly do: Yet thus much is evident to all that have but the leaſt inſight into the Conſtitution
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94358:14"/>of our Government, that no Nation under Heaven hath been more Sollicitous for their Sovereigns Honour and Safety, none more tender of their Princes Reputation and Government than Our Own; and therefore no Country hath better Laws, and no Laws make better Proviſion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People</hi> than theſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Our <hi>Conſtitution</hi> is the <hi>Happieſt</hi> and <hi>Safeſt</hi> both for the One and the other, if we had but Eyes open to ſee it, and Hearts thankful enough to Acknowledge it as we ought.</p>
            <p>No War can be juſtifiable, but what is begun and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by a <hi>Lawful Power,</hi> and the People of <hi>England</hi> will always want that in their taking up Arms againſt their Prince; for the Law hath made all Reſiſtance of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Illegal, by acknowledging the Power of the Sword to be ſolely in the King; ſo that no man hath Power, or any Pretence of Power now to take up Arms, but by the <hi>Royal Authority,</hi> which be ſure the King will never Commiſſion againſt himſelf; or if he ſhould, the Grant is void in its own Nature, as being inconſiſtent with the Eſſentials of Sovereign Power, which cannot be <hi>Sovereign</hi> unleſs it be <hi>Irreſiſtable</hi> too; and ſuch is that Power which our Kings are inveſted withall, and which the People do Recognize every time they take the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and declare their Abhorrence of that Traiterous Poſition, <hi>Of taking up Arms againſt the King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Or any that are Commiſſioned by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 3. The <hi>Methods</hi> of <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> and Open Force, (let the Enemies of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> ſay what they will) are the moſt Unſafe and Impolitick Courſe we can take for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Liberty and Property; which will appear if we conſider,</p>
            <p>§. 1. War, <hi>Civil War</hi> eſpecially, is one of the moſt For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Violations of Publick Laws and Liberty; for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of taking up Arms for the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Subject, they do hereby but <hi>Invade</hi> thoſe of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94358:15"/>other men, and <hi>Hazard</hi> their own. Now the open Breach of the Laws is no good Method for attaining their End; the expoſing our Liberties to the chance of War is the worſt courſe we can take to Preſerve them, and the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding other mens Properties, but an ill way of Securing our own: For this makes every man guilty of that Crime which he is jealous of in his <hi>Prince,</hi> namely, the becoming <hi>Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſive, Regardleſs</hi> of the <hi>Commonweal</hi> and <hi>Publick Good;</hi> This makes Subjects more <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> than the moſt <hi>Abſolute Monarch,</hi> and <hi>Popular Fury</hi> of much worſe conſequence than any unbounded <hi>Tyranny</hi> whatſoever; inſomuch as the Remedy proves alwayes worſe than the Diſeaſe, and Ends many times in the open Shame and juſt Puniſhment of the firſt Authors and Abettors thereof: And tho the Prince may chance to fall in the Crowd, yet this is ſtill ſo much the worſe for the Subject, who ſeldom gets any thing thereby; for Rebellion and Diſobedience under a good Prince is oft-times puniſh'd with the Succeſſion of a Bad one. This hath been our Caſe once already, when we got <hi>many Ill Maſters</hi> in the room of <hi>one Good one.</hi> Let us take heed therefore of thoſe Commotions for which of late we have ſmarted ſo ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; let us have a care we do not by our Mutiny and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſturb the Government, and thereby Sin our ſelve into a worſe Condition than that we pretend to Fear at preſent.</p>
            <p>§ 2. Reſiſtance is a Method that God ſeldom bleſſes, and rarely Thrives with any Number of Men, that ſhall be ſo wicked as to make uſe of it.</p>
            <p>The Safety of a Nation, and the Security of Government conſiſts more in Gods <hi>Providence</hi> and the Peoples <hi>Quietneſs</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> thereto, than in their <hi>Greateſt Force</hi> and <hi>Strongeſt Oppoſition;</hi> for when they have done all they can, Ten to One but things return again into their Old Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel. Notwithſtanding all we can do, God will govern the World; <hi>The Lord will reign as King upon Earth, let the People be never ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly.</hi> After all our Stirs and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94358:15"/>things ſhall go, not as we, but as God will have them; This <hi>Conſideration</hi> alone hath bore up the Spirits of the <hi>Beſt</hi> and <hi>Wiſeſt</hi> Men in all Ages, after they had for many years <hi>Wearied</hi> and <hi>Puzled</hi> themſelves with the <hi>Intricacy</hi> of Humane Affairs.</p>
            <p>Pray conſider, what do People commonly get by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and ſuch like Violent Attempts, except it be to Rebell themſelves into <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> or Sin a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into thoſe very <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> which they are apt to be ſo Jealous and Apprehenſive of.</p>
            <p>What hath <hi>France</hi> got by all her <hi>Civil Wars</hi> and <hi>Broils,</hi> (whereof that Nation had good ſtore formerly) that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranical Yoke</hi> which ſhe would have ſhook off thereby, doth but ſit the Cloſer upon her Neck, and Grates more heavily than ever; And the Religion which they ſo eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended for, is now in great Danger to be utterly loſt and extinguiſh'd; except a greater Power than that of Man, be pleaſed to interpoſe miraculouſly on its behalf.</p>
            <p>And to come nearer home; Pray tell me, What have we of this Nation got by our late <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural Wars,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Peoples Succeſs againſt the Government? What did we then purchaſe by all the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> that we ſpent for ſo many years, but only <hi>Servitude</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> which was the very thing we pretended to Fear from our <hi>Lawful Prince.</hi> What did we get by Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Murdering of <hi>one Good King,</hi> but the Uſurpation of <hi>Many</hi> in his room? What by diſſolving the <hi>Ancient Frame</hi> of Government, but the erecting of ſeveral <hi>Tyrannies</hi> in his ſtead. What got we by Baniſhing our <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and Forcing them into a <hi>Strange Land,</hi> but to ſend them for Shelter and Refuge to the <hi>Enemies</hi> of our <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Religion?</hi> And ſhall we ſtill be at the ſame lay? Shall we be ſtill playing with the Flames, which have ſcorch'd us ſo terribly already? This is to be worſe than Children, if after having been once burnt, we do not for ever after Dread the Fire. God forbid then, that any among us ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94358:16"/>in the leaſt Favour, much leſs Attempt over again the ſame Violent Courſes which have been the Occaſion of ſo great Unhappineſs to theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>After we had once ſhook the Government, and ſubverted the Ancient Frame and happy Conſtitution thereof, how long was it before the Nation could <hi>Settle</hi> it ſelf again? We chang'd and ſhifted ſo oft, till we were in fear of Disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Government, and every man forc'd to ſtand upon his <hi>Guard</hi> as in time of War, and to take care of his own Defence, as they began at laſt to do in this <hi>City:</hi> So much cauſe they ſaw of Fear, and ſo little of Hope, or any thing certain to Truſt unto; and this was our Condition for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years together. For <hi>Rebellion,</hi> like an <hi>Inauſpicious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nluckey Configuration</hi> of the Heavens, doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all its ill Effects at once, but continues its <hi>Malignant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence</hi> a long time after, as it did then, nay, I may ſay, as it doth ſtill; for unto our late Uncivil Commotions we may impute a great Part of our Preſent Fears and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Unſettlement and Diſtraction.</p>
            <p>Now to draw towards a Concluſion: Seeing theſe things are ſo, what remains for us to do in our <hi>Preſent Circumſtances,</hi> but to leave the Government of the World to the Maker of it, and the Management of Publick Affairs to thoſe, whom the good Providence of God hath ſet over us. It belongs to our Governours to Rule and Reform the State, and to God to Over-rule and Amend what may poſſibly be amiſs in them. We are not oblig'd to do God more Service than he hath allow'd us to do, or will thank us for, when we have done: We may <hi>Exceed</hi> and Over-act our Parts in one <hi>Extream,</hi> as well as be too Remiſs and <hi>Defective</hi> in the other; hereby we leave no room for <hi>Suffering,</hi> if we may <hi>Oppoſe,</hi> nor make uſe of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> while we are unwilling to have them exercis'd and undergo the Trial.</p>
            <p>To be <hi>peaceable</hi> in <hi>peaceable Times,</hi> to be <hi>Loyal</hi> when there is no <hi>great Number</hi> of Examples to the contrary, to be <hi>Still</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> when the <hi>Genius</hi> and <hi>Complexion</hi> of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94358:16"/>whole Nation is ſo, this is not Thank-worthy, 'tis no leſs our preſent Intereſt, than Duty ſo to be; the moſt Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous can be content to be Quiet, and Boaſt of their Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſuch a Juncture as this: But to give proof of a Quiet Temper and Diſpoſition, to adhere to Principles of Peace and Loyalty when the whole Nation is preſt with contrary Extreams, and diſtracted with Oppoſite Factions on either hand, this is an Argument of a Good Man, Good Chriſtian, and Good Subject indeed; of one that is fix'd to his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and bears a Good Conſcience in all things, tho he may be ill thought of for his Pains, and badly treated by either <hi>Extream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis therefore the <hi>Glory</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> (for which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Reproaches of many have fallen upon her) 'tis her <hi>Glory,</hi> I ſay, however, as it always was of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> that neither of them did ever encourage Diſturbance or Commotion in the State, or gave the leaſt countenance to Force and Oppoſition againſt Government: Why then ſhe ſhould be Cenſur'd ſo ſeverely for adhering to thoſe very Principles which were the <hi>Credit</hi> of Religion, and the Ornament of its firſt Profeſſours and Reformers, I do not underſtand. For People to brand us for Papiſts, or ſuſpect us of Confederacy with the Common Enemy, for aſſerting a Doctrine that is <hi>purely Chriſtian,</hi> and directly <hi>Oppoſite</hi> to that of <hi>Rome,</hi> is to reflect upon our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which acknowledge as much as this comes to: At this rate what may not People talk, who think <hi>their Tongues are their own,</hi> and they may uſe them as they pleaſe; they may as well ſay the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> of the Church were a company of <hi>Heathens,</hi> for perſuading the Chriſtians of their time to ſubmit themſelves to the Tyranny of Pagan Princes and Perſecutours without Reſiſtance; as to ſay, that we are <hi>Well-willers</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Ill-willers</hi> to our <hi>Country,</hi> for doing the <hi>ſame Thing,</hi> and going upon the <hi>ſame Principles</hi> as they did; nay, they may as well ſay that Chriſt himſelf had a Deſign upon all Governments under Heaven, becauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94358:17"/>he hath enjoyn'd Submiſſion to the Higher Powers, and made Reſiſtance Unlawful under the worſt of Princes.</p>
            <p>But if the Principles of our <hi>Church,</hi> and of thoſe men who charge her ſo heavily, were but throughly weigh'd and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd together, we ſhould quickly ſee which of the <hi>two</hi> bids faireſt for ſuch a <hi>Character,</hi> and doth moſt deſerve to lye under ſuch a Suſpicion. However, let men Judge and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as they pleaſe, as their Intereſts may ſway, or Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons incline them, yet, ſince the Author of our Religion hath made Reſiſtance a <hi>Sin,</hi> and Subjection a Duty upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, the Miniſters of Chriſt (if they would be found Faithful) ought to connive at <hi>this Sin</hi> no more than at any other; nor yet ſuffer the <hi>Guilt</hi> thereof to lye upon their Peoples Souls, without warning them of the great <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> of it, and putting them in mind of their Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Governours, as oft as need ſhall require.</p>
            <p>In a Word, As we ought to <hi>Teach,</hi> ſo 'tis your part to <hi>Learn</hi> your Duty towards <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> toward <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> as now eſtabliſh'd. Be not therefore fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of your Duty by the Apprehenſion of <hi>Romiſh Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> on the one hand, nor by the Reproach of <hi>Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Faction</hi> on the other; Think not ſlight of <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> as ſome lately have done, tho with little <hi>Credit</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>themſelves</hi> or their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> nor yet run into the <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Guilt</hi> of any Temptation in the <hi>World;</hi> Do not ſhrink from the Principles of <hi>True Chriſtian Subjection,</hi> nor of <hi>old Engliſh Allegiance:</hi> but learn of an Apoſtle, <hi>to Fear God and Honour the King;</hi> or take the Counſel of one of the Greateſt of Kings, and Wiſeſt of Men; wherewith I ſhall ſhut up this Diſcourſe. <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. <hi>My Son, Fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change; for their Calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knows the Ruine of them Both.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:94358:17"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books printed for and ſold by <hi>William Crooke</hi> Bookſeller, at the Sign of the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Tem-Bar,</hi> nigh the Paſſage into the <hi>Temple</hi> by <hi>Devereux</hi>-Court, 1685.</head>
            <list>
               <head>DIVINITY.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>BRevis Demonſtratio,</hi> being the Truth of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proved by Reaſon, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> price bound 10 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Primitive Inſtitution,</hi> ſhewing the Antiquity and Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Catechiſing, together with its ſuitableneſs to heal the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the Church. By <hi>L. Addiſon. D. D.</hi> and Dean of <hi>Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. A Sermon preach'd at the Funeral of a Sober Religious Man, ſound drown'd in a Pit. In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. Mr. <hi>Howel</hi>'s Viſitation-Sermon before the Biſhop of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. Dr. <hi>Haſcard</hi>'s two Sermons, the one on the Fifth of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the other before the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> both in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>6. Mr. <hi>Manningham</hi>'s two Sermons, one before the Lord Mayor, the other at St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> In quarto.</item>
               <item>7. A Sermon preached at the <hi>Savoy</hi> Church in French, and ſince printed in French and Engliſh, twelves, price bound 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>A Modeſt Plea for the Clergy,</hi> wherein is conſidered the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why the Clergy are ſo contemned and neglected. By <hi>L. A. D. D.</hi> and Dean of <hi>Litchfield.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> his Catechiſm, Greek, Latin, and Engliſh, with a <hi>Praxis</hi> of all the Greek Words therein contained. In octavo. price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> proving that Chriſt and his Apoſtles were Prophets: written by the directions of, and recommended to the Preſs, by the late <hi>Peter Gunning,</hi> then Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely.</hi> In octavo. price 3 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>The King-killing Doctrine of the Jeſuites,</hi> in a ſincere Diſcourſe to the <hi>French King;</hi> written by a <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi> In quarto. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12. <hi>Juſtifying Faith;</hi> or the Faith by which the Juſt do live, together with the excellency of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book.</hi> In octavo. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94358:18"/>
               <item>13. <hi>Mercy Tryumphant,</hi> or the Kingdom of Chriſt enlarged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the narrow bounds which have been wont to be ſet to it. By <hi>Ed. Lane. M. A.</hi> and Rector of <hi>Sparſhals.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14. <hi>Du. Moulin</hi>'s <hi>Reflections reverberated,</hi> being a full anſwer to the damning Doctrine of Dr. <hi>Lewis de Moulin:</hi> alſo, a Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Edmond Hickeringill</hi> againſt the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</hi> By <hi>E. Lane,</hi> &amp;c. In quarto. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15. A Diſcourſe about Conſcience, relating to the preſent Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences among us, in oppoſition to both extremes of Popery and Fanaticiſm. In quarto. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16. A Thankſgiving-Sermon for the Diſcovery of the late Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Plot. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 9. 1683. By <hi>John Hariſon, D. D.</hi> Rector of <hi>Pulborrow.</hi> quarto.</item>
               <item>17. An Introduction to the Sacrament. or, a ſhort, plain, and ſafe way to the Communion-Table, being an Inſtruction for the worthy receiving the Lords Supper; Collected for, and familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addreſſed to every particular Communicant. By <hi>L. Addiſon, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Litchfield.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>18. The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion the ſafe way to Salvation: or, an Anſwer to a Book entituled, <hi>Mercy and Truth, or Charity maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> by Catholicks which pretend to prove the contrary; together with the Apoſtolical Inſtitution of Epiſcopacy; as alſo nine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on ſpecial occaſions. By <hi>William Chillingworth,</hi> M. A. of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> the fifth Edition; to which is now added Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Reaſons againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> to perſwade Mr. <hi>L.</hi> to return to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> In <hi>fol.</hi> price 14 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>HISTORY.</head>
               <item>1. <hi>AN Inſtitution of general Hiſtory,</hi> or the Hiſtory of the World; being a compleat Body thereof, in two Volumes, by <hi>W. Howel,</hi> late Chancellour of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> In <hi>folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Hiſtorical Collections;</hi> being an account of the Proceedings of the four laſt Parliaments of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by <hi>H. Townſend,</hi> Eſq; in <hi>folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Clelia,</hi> the whole Work, in five parts; written in <hi>French,</hi> now put into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in <hi>folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Scarron</hi>'s Comical Romance; being an Hiſtorical account of a company of <hi>Stage-players,</hi> full of variety of <hi>Novels,</hi> rare <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures,</hi> amorous <hi>Intrigues,</hi> &amp;c. being both witty and pleaſant. In <hi>folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>The Life of</hi> Thomas Hobbs <hi>of</hi> Malmsbury, written by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Latin, ſince tranſlated into Engliſh. In <hi>folio,</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94358:18"/>
               <item>6. <hi>Megalopſichy;</hi> being a particular and exact Account of the laſt ſeventeen years of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, both Military and Civil; the firſt written by Sir <hi>W. Monſon,</hi> one of the ſaid Queens Admirals; the ſecond written by <hi>H. Townſend,</hi> Eſq; a Member of her laſt Parliament. Wherein is a true and faithful Relation of all the expeditious attempts, deſigns, ſucceſſes, and errours, both of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> in the Wars, from the year 1585, to the ſaid Queens Death; with a full account of the eminent <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Debates,</hi> &amp;c. in the ſaid time: To which is added, Dr. <hi>Parry</hi>'s Tryal in the year 1584, all written at the time of the <hi>Actions,</hi> by Perſons that were eminently acting therein. <hi>folio,</hi> price bound 10 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>A Voyage into the</hi> Levant, being a Relation of a Journey late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> by Sir <hi>Henry Blunt,</hi> twelves. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>A deſcription</hi> of Candia, with an exact account of the laſt Siege and Surrender of it to the <hi>Turks.</hi> In octavo. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. A Diſcourſe of the Dukedom of <hi>Modena,</hi> containing the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, Antiquity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of that Dukedom. In quarto. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. <hi>The preſent ſtate of</hi> London, containing the Antiquity, Fame, Walls, Rivers, Gates, Churches, Bridge, with the Cuſtoms and Infranchiſements. By <hi>J. Bridal,</hi> Eſq; price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>The Wonders of the Peak in</hi> Darby-ſhire, commonly called the <hi>Devils Arſe of Peak.</hi> By <hi>Tho. Hobbs,</hi> octavo. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12. <hi>The Life and Death of</hi> Mahomet, being the firſt eſtate of <hi>Mahometiſm,</hi> ſhewing all the deſigns that that Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet</hi> had to carry on and ſettle the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Religion; written by <hi>L. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſon, D. D.</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13. <hi>The Connexion;</hi> being Collections of ſome principal matters in the Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> being the time that nothing of this nature is printed, being betwixt the end of <hi>Megalopſichy,</hi> or the laſt ſeventeen years of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the beginning of Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth, Heath, Nalſon, Whitlock,</hi> and others, price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14. The Moors <hi>baffled;</hi> being a Diſcourſe of the Government of <hi>Tangier,</hi> under the Earl of <hi>Tiviot;</hi> ſhewing the ſubtilty and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of both parties: written by Dr. <hi>Addiſon,</hi> who lived there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, quarto. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15. All the Works of <hi>Homer,</hi> both <hi>Iliads</hi> and <hi>Odyſſes,</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of <hi>Greek</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Hobbs</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16. Conſiderations on the Loyalty, Religion, Manners, and Reputation of <hi>Thomas Hobbs,</hi> octavo. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>17. The <hi>Memoirs</hi> and rare <hi>Adventures</hi> of <hi>Henrietta Sylvia Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liere,</hi> a great Lady in <hi>France,</hi> now living, written <hi>by her ſelf,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:94358:19"/>ſix parts in <hi>French,</hi> and now tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>18. Tho. Hobbs <hi>Angli Malmbs. Vita,</hi> being an account of <hi>Mr. Hobbs,</hi> of the Books he wrote, of the times when, and the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof; of the Books and Authors againſt him, of his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, Acquaintance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> part wrote by himſelf, the reſt by Dr. <hi>B.</hi> in octavo. printed 1681.</item>
               <item>19. <hi>Behemoth,</hi> being the Hiſtory of the Civil Wars of <hi>England,</hi> and the Councels and Artifices by which they were carried on, from 1640, to 1660. Printed now from his own perfect Copy, in which is many pages more than was in the former <hi>Counterfeit Edition;</hi> none of which Editions before this, had leſs than <hi>a thouſand faults</hi> in them, whole Lines leſt out in <hi>a hundred places,</hi> which did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly pervert the ſence of the Author <hi>Tho. Hobbs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20. The <hi>Tracts</hi> of Mr. <hi>Tho. Hobbs</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> in two Volumes in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. gathering nine of his Treatiſes together, which are alſo to be had ſingle, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>His Life</hi> in Latin. 2. His <hi>Conſiderations</hi> on his Loyalty, Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. His Art of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> 4. His Dialogue about the Common Law of <hi>England.</hi> 5. His ten Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of <hi>Natural Philoſophy.</hi> 6. His <hi>Civil Wars</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the perfect Edition. 7. His Hiſtorical Narration of <hi>Hereſy.</hi> 8. His An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Biſhop <hi>Brambal</hi> in defence of his <hi>Leviathan.</hi> 9. His ſeven Problems, with an Apology for his writings to the King, price bound 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>21. <hi>A New Survey</hi> of the preſent State of the World, newly written in French, and now tranſlated into Engliſh, in octavo.</item>
               <item>22. <hi>Compendium Geographicum:</hi> or, a more exact, plain, and eaſie Introduction into all Geography than yet extant, after the lateſt Diſcoveries and new Alteration; very uſeful, eſpecially for young Noblemen and Gentlemen; the like not printed in Engliſh. By <hi>P. Chamberlayne</hi> of the Inner Temple, Gent. the ſecond Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Additions, twelves price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>23. <hi>Bucaniers of America:</hi> or, a true Account of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Aſſaults committed of late years upon the Coaſts of the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> by the <hi>Bucamers</hi> of <hi>Jamaica</hi> and <hi>Tortuga,</hi> both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> &amp;c. Written in <hi>Dutch, Spaniſh,</hi> &amp;c. And now put into <hi>Engliſh;</hi> the ſecond Edition, with the Addition of Captain <hi>Cookes,</hi> and another Relation to it, in quarto. <hi>Now is newly printed the ſecond Volume of the</hi> Bucaniers <hi>of</hi> America. In quarto. price 6 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>24. <hi>The preſent State of the Jews,</hi> wherein is contained an exact Account of their Cuſtoms, Secular and Religious; to which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed a ſummary Diſcourſe of the <hi>Miſna, Talmud,</hi> and <hi>Gemara.</hi> By <hi>L. Addiſon</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Litchfield,</hi> and Archdeacon of <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> twelves. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>25. <hi>French Intrigues:</hi> or, the Hiſtory of their Deluſory Promiſes ſince the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty: printed in <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Cologne,</hi> and now made. <hi>Engliſh</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94358:19"/>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
